“Jehovah is great and most worthy of . . .”
「エホバは偉大で 大いに…」
「賛美すべき方！」
“. . . praise”!
その通り
Very good.
“. . . worthy of praise in the city of our God,
「私たちの神の都 聖なる山で
“in his holy mountain.
“Beautiful in its loftiness,
高い所にあって美しく
the joy of the whole earth, is Mount”—
地上の全ての人の喜びとなるのは…」
Who can tell me?
何て言う山かな？
“Mount Zion”!
シオンの山！
Both of you have been paying good attention.
2人ともすごいね
じゃあ シオンの山はどこにあるの？
Now, where is Mount Zion?
Right here, Father. Right here.
ここだよパパ ここにある
Where?
どこ？ 見えないよ ほんとかな？
I don’t see it. Are you sure?
No, Father, we live on Mount Zion.
今いるここがシオンの山でしょ
Are you saying we live on a mountain?
じゃあ 今みんな山の上？
そういうこと
Yes.
What is so special about Mount Zion?
シオンの山ってどんなとこ？
知ってる！ 知ってる！
I know! I know!
じゃあ教えて
Tell me, my dear.
ダビデ王が住んでたとこ
エホバはこう言ったの
This is where King David lived.
Jehovah said:
‘I have put my king upon Zion,
「私は聖なる山シオンに王を立てた」
my holy mountain.’
契約の箱も持ってきたよ
The priests brought the Ark here.
Hamutal, where did we get such studious children?
ハムタル この子たち
いったいどこの子？
Just like their father.
きっとお父さんが立派なのよ
Come on, children.
あなたたち いらっしゃい
Aw!
え～っ！
Oh!
あ～ぁ
Zephaniah, today my little son
ゼパニヤ
今日息子が原っぱで見つけた
found this in a field and brought it home.
拾ってきたんだ
They’re filling the holy city with their filthy idols.
聖なる都市は偶像で満ちています
Everywhere I look, I see Baal images
どこを見てもバアルの像があるし
and smoke on the high places.
高い場所からは煙が上っている
The smell of their incense makes me sick!
あの香の臭いはもう我慢できない
I’ve been king for 12 years now.
王になって12年
It’s time to act!
行動する時が来た！
I want to finish the cleansing work my grandfather started.
祖父が始めた改革を成し遂げたい
You will need Jehovah’s help.
エホバの助けが必要です
I know.
分かってる
そのことを昼も夜も祈ってる
I’ve been praying about it day and night.
Good.
いいですね
I will issue a proclamation:
布告を出します
Let the word go forth that we will rid this land of idolatry!
この地から偶像を一掃することを
人々に伝えます！
よそじゃもっと安かったぞ
I’ve seen these cheaper.
Take it or leave it.
買わないならいいわよ
強気の商売だね
You keep raising your prices.
ここからだ！
We start here!
No!
ワーッ！
この国の偶像は全てこうなる
This is what we will do to every false god in the land.
Father—
父さん
Father, wake up!
父さん 起きて！
Father, come on, this is no time to be sleeping.
父さん 大変だ！
寝てる場合じゃないよ
Josiah is on a campaign against all the other gods except Jehovah.
ヨシヤはエホバ以外の神
すべてを破壊し始めた
What?
何だと？
ヨシヤは自分の国を滅ぼすつもりか
Josiah is upending his own kingdom?
This will not go down as easily as they think.
あいつらが考えるほど
簡単にはいかないだろう
Does he think people will give up their customs?
人々が生き方を変えられる
とでも思っているのか
their rituals? their whole way of life?
儀式や習慣は 染みついている
He’s a fool.
気にするな
Baal will rescue us.
バアルが救ってくださる
Baal will rescue us?
バアルが救ってくださる？
Father, look around!
父さん 何言ってるの！
All over Judah and Jerusalem,
ヨシヤはユダとエルサレムで
バアルの像を破壊してるんだよ
Josiah is destroying Baal images.
They can’t even rescue themselves!
バアルは自分すら救えない！
And the people—
そして人々は 人々は
ヨシヤを支持してる！
The people are supporting him!
Go ahead and doubt, you disrespectful child.
興奮するな この親不孝者が
You have become disloyal to Baal and to me,
お前は バアルにも
お前を誕生させた父親にも反抗するのか
your father, who gave you life.
Never mind, I’ll come up with a plan.
心配するな いい考えがある
王妃ハムタル様…
少しいいですか…
My lady Hamutal, a word with you, please.
A word with you, please!
話を聞いてください
Ben-Mattan!
ベン・マタンじゃない！
What do you want?
どうしたんですか？
お願いです
Please, tell the king he must stop what he’s doing.
王に 考え直すように言ってください
This is madness.
とても正気とは思えません
He’s endangering himself,
王はご自分や家族
his family, and our entire nation.
そして国全体を危険にさらしています
Josiah’s campaign against Baal worshippers
王の バアル崇拝者に対する仕打ちは
is a campaign against Baal himself.
バアル自身に対するものです
Oh, Ben-Mattan, you and your disgusting idols.
これ以上私に近づくと
護衛たちが黙っていませんよ
Get away from me before I have the guards arrest you.
お許しください
Forgive me.
I beg you, just another word, please.
あと一言聞いてください
お願いします
ハムタル様
Hamutal, I’m only telling you this for your own safety.
あなたのために申し上げているのです
王のお父様に起きたあの恐ろしいことが
It’d be terrible if something were to happen to the king
王の身にまた起きるかもしれません
like what happened to his father.
Hamutal,
そして あなたの子供たちにも…
think of your children.
Baal worshippers are no match for Jehovah, Hamutal.
バアル崇拝者が エホバに
太刀打ちすることなどできない
Please don’t be fearful.
心配しなくていい
But this campaign has gone on for a year.
でも この活動を始めてもう1年
How long do we have to endure this?
いつまで続くのかしら…
However long it takes.
でも やり遂げなければ
Yes.
なんですか
My lord, Zephaniah the prophet has arrived.
主よ 預言者ゼパニヤが
どなたかを連れて来られました
He brought someone with him.
Thank you.
分かった 謁見の間に通しなさい
I’ll see them in the throne room.
子供たちを見守っていてくれ
Better check on the children.
Please don’t show your concern in front of them.
心配そうな様子を見せないように
エホバ 私は極端ですか
Jehovah, have I gone too far?
My own grandfather didn’t succeed
祖父のマナセでさえこの国から
高い場所を一掃できませんでした
in ridding the land of the high places.
How can I do this?
どうすればいいんですか
My lord, this is Jeremiah from Anathoth.
主よ これがアナトテのエレミヤです
The man whom Jehovah has called to be a prophet, welcome.
エホバから選ばれた
預言者ですね ようこそ
ヨシヤ王 忠実な者はみな
あなたを支持しています
King Josiah, all the faithful ones
support your campaign against idolatry.
We have done as you directed, my lord.
主よ 私たちは指示通りに行いました
And since you began this campaign 18 months ago,
そして 1年半前に始めて以来
you have gained many supporters.
この活動の支持者は増えています
This is true.
その通りですが
Yet, many have continued worshipping Baal.
今なお多くの人々が
バアルを崇拝していますし
Men like Ben-Mattan pose a great threat.
ベン・マタンのような危険人物もいます
The people may even resort to violence
私たちに危害を加えてくる
可能性もあります
to oppose this great work.
その通りだ
No doubt.
My lord,
主よ
do you feel that you may not have
この仕事を完了できない
とでも思っているのですか
what it takes to complete such a task?
Restoring pure worship will take much more effort,
清い崇拝の回復にはさらに多くの
努力が必要だが
but it’s the right thing to do.
それはすべきことだ
You’re right, Josiah.
その通りです
But you’re not doing this in human strength;
これは人間の仕事ではありません
Jehovah is on your side.
エホバが共にいてくださいます
He will give you the courage, wisdom,
あなたに勇気と知恵と
力を与えてくださいます
and strength to complete this work.
When I expressed doubt in my own abilities,
エホバは私にこうおっしゃいました
Jehovah told me: “Do not say, ‘I am just a boy.’”
自分は「『少年にすぎない』
と言っては」ならない
But Jehovah spoke to you directly, Jeremiah.
エホバはあなたに直接話された
私のことも支えてくださるだろうか
How can I be sure that he’ll back me up that way?
Jeremiah just told me
エレミヤによると 約300年前
ヤラベアム王が
of a prophecy given hundreds of years ago,
北王国に祭壇を設けた時に
告げられた預言があるようです
after King Jeroboam set up his own altar in the northern kingdom.
“By the word of Jehovah,
「ヤラベアムが犠牲の煙を
立ち上らせるため
“a man of God came from Judah to Bethel
祭壇のそばに立っていた時
“while Jeroboam was standing by the altar
神に仕える人が
ユダからベテルにやって来た
“to make sacrificial smoke.
“Then he called out
その人はエホバの命令により
“against the altar by the word of Jehovah and said:
祭壇に向かって大声で言った
“‘O altar, altar!
「祭壇よ 祭壇よ！
“‘This is what Jehovah says:
エホバはこう言っている
“‘“Look! A son named Josiah
『ヨシヤという男の子が
ダビデ家に生まれる
“‘“will be born to the house of David!
その人は 高い場所の祭司たちを
あなたの上で犠牲として捧げる
“‘“He will sacrifice on you the priests of the high places,
“‘“those making sacrificial smoke on you,
あなたの上で犠牲の煙を
立ち上らせている
and he will burn human bones on you.”’”
祭司たちをである』」
So do not waver in a lack of faith, Josiah.
ですからヨシヤ 弱気に
ならないでください
Become powerful by faith,
私たちの父アブラハムのように
信仰によって強くなってください
like our father Abraham.
Jehovah also spoke to me, Josiah.
エホバは私にもこう言われました
He said:
「この場所から
“I will wipe out from this place every vestige of Baal,
バアルの痕跡をことごとく消し去る
祭司たちを また外国の神の
祭司たちの名を消し去る……
“the name of the foreign-god priests along with the priests . . .
“I will call to account the princes,
私は責任を問う
“the sons of the king, and all those wearing foreign clothing.
高官たち 王の子たち
“. . . Neither their silver nor their gold will . . . save them . . .
外国の服装をする者全てに……
銀も金も助けにならない……
He will bring to nothing all the gods of the earth.”
地上の全ての神を除き去る」
シャファン 清めの活動は順調ですが
Shaphan, the cleansing campaign has gone well,
but the temple is in disrepair.
神殿は荒れたままです
It has been neglected for decades.
何十年も放置されたままです
I heartily agree, my lord.
おっしゃる通りです
Go up to Hilkiah, the high priest,
大祭司ヒルキヤの所に行き
let him collect all the silver
エホバの家に持ち込まれた全ての銀を
集めるように言ってください
that is brought into the house of Jehovah.
それを 神殿修復に携わる
監督たちに渡して
Give it to those appointed over the work
to repair the damage.
材木と切り石を買うよう伝えてください
Tell them to buy timbers and hewn stones.
素晴らしいです！
Very good, my lord!
会計はだれが担当しますか
シャファンですか
And who should keep account of the funds?
Shaphan?
No, Joah, no accounting should be required for the silver.
ヨアハ 会計係は必要ありません
All these men are trustworthy.
信頼できる人ばかりです
Yes, my lord, as you wish.
分かりました おっしゃる通りに
The day my grandfather died,
祖父が死んだ日に
神殿について話してくれました
he spoke of the temple.
I kept this safe all these years,
私はこれをずっと大事にしてきました
hoping one day I could glorify Jehovah’s house.
エホバの家を栄光で
満たすことを夢見て…
Today is that day.
ついにその日が来た
ヒルキヤ！ どうされましたか
Hilkiah! What’s wrong?
シャファン
Shaphan, I found the book of the Law in the house of Jehovah.
エホバの家で律法の書を見つけました
The book of the Law?
律法の書？
I’ve never seen these passages before.
見たことのない内容だ
今すぐヨシヤ王に渡してください
Take this scroll to King Josiah immediately.
資材に関しては 今のところ
予定より早く届いており
Materials—as far as that goes,
we are ahead of schedule for the most part.
工程は順調です
But there are a few items that just haven’t come in yet.
ただ いくつか搬入が
遅れている資材もあります
来週までに届いて
くれればいいのですが…
As long as we get them in the next week or so—
My lord.
わが主よ
Shaphan!
シャファン！順調ですか
How is the renovation coming?
Your servants are doing everything that was assigned to them.
皆 割り当てられた
務めを果たしています
They have poured out the money
エホバの家に集まったお金も
that was found in the house of Jehovah,
and they have handed it over
修復工事のために任命された
人たちに渡しています
to the appointed men and to those doing the work.
Very well.
素晴らしい
何かありましたか
Is there something else?
はい 主よ
Yes, my lord.
There is a book that Hilkiah the priest has given me.
祭司ヒルキヤが書を見つけました
What book?
書を見つけた？
モーセが記したもののようです
They appear to be the words of Moses, my lord.
Read it to us, then!
読んでください！
“These are the regulations
「以下の規定と法規を
注意して守りなさい…
“and the judicial decisions that you should be careful to carry out . . .
皆さんが追い立てる国民は
“You should completely destroy all the places
高い山や丘や生い茂った木の下で
神々に仕えています
“where the nations you will dispossess have served their gods,
“whether on the high mountains
それらの場所全てを
“or on the hills or under any luxuriant tree.
完全に破壊すべきです
“You should pull down their altars,
彼らの祭壇を打ち壊し
“shatter their sacred pillars,
聖柱を打ち砕き 聖木を火で焼き
“burn their sacred poles in the fire,
神々の彫像を切り倒し
“and cut down the graven images of their gods,
その神々の名前を
そこから消し去るべきです」
obliterating their very names from that place.”
Argh!
うぁーっ！
Go!
みんな ヒルキヤと一緒に行って
All of you along with Hilkiah,
この書に記された言葉について
エホバに尋ねてください
inquire of Jehovah concerning the words
of the book that has been found,
for Jehovah’s rage is great
父祖たちがそのおきてを守らず
それを行わなかったために
because our forefathers did not carry out the word of Jehovah
エホバの怒りは激しいからです
by observing all that is written in this book.
The prophetess Huldah lives nearby in the Second Quarter.
女預言者フルダは
第2地区に住んでいます
I’ll ask Hilkiah to meet us there.
ヒルキヤに伝えましょう
This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says:
イスラエルの神エホバは
こう言っておられます
「あなたたちを私のもとに
遣わした人に言いなさい……
“Tell the man who sent you to me:
“‘. . . I will bring calamity on this place
『私はこの場所と住民に災難をもたらす
“‘and its inhabitants,
“‘all the curses that are written in the book
ユダの王の前で読まれた
書物に書かれている災いを
“‘that they read before the king of Judah.
“‘Because they have abandoned me
彼らが私を捨て
“‘and are making sacrifices smoke
ほかの神々のために犠牲を焼いて煙にし
“‘to other gods in order to offend me . . . ,
行いによって私を怒らせたので……
“‘my rage will pour out on this place
私はこの場所に怒りを浴びせる
and it will not be extinguished.’”
その怒りが消えることはない』」
But to the king of Judah . . . ,
ですが イスラエルの神エホバは
ユダの王にこう言われます
this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says:
“Because your heart was responsive
「あなたは……心が柔らかで
“and you humbled yourself before God on hearing his words
神の言葉を聞いた時
その前で謙遜になった……
“. . . and ripped your garments apart
衣服を引き裂き 泣いたので
“and wept before me,
私エホバはあなたの祈りを聞いた」
I also have heard you.”
“I also have heard you . . .
“That is why . . . you will be laid in your grave in peace,
「『それで ……あなたは安らかに
自分の墓に入る
“and your eyes will not see all the calamity
あなたは私がこの場所……に
もたらす災いを全く見ない』」
that I will bring on this place.”
Praised be Jehovah, our merciful God,
憐み深い私たちの神
エホバがほめたたえられますように
for holding back his wrath.
Summon all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem.
ユダとエルサレムの全ての長老たちに
エホバの家に来るよう伝えてください
Have them come up to the house of Jehovah.
「注意して 私が命じるこれらの
全ての言葉に従いなさい
“Be careful to obey all these words
“that I am commanding you,
あなたの神エホバから見て
“so that it may always go well with you and your sons after you,
正しくて良いことを行って
あなたとあなたの子たちにとって
“because you are doing what is good and right
いつも物事がうまくいくためです」
“in the eyes of Jehovah your God.
「あなたが追い立てようとしている国民を
エホバ神が全滅させ……たなら……
“When Jehovah your God annihilates
“the nations that you are to dispossess,
“. . . do not ask about their gods, saying,
彼らの神々について尋ね
『これらの国民はどのように
神々に仕えていたのか
“‘How were these nations accustomed to serve their gods?’
私も同じようにしよう』
と言ってはなりません……
“. . . Because they do for their gods
“every detestable thing that Jehovah hates,
彼らは エホバが憎む忌まわしいこと
全てを自分たちの神々のために行い
“even burning their sons and their daughters
息子や娘を火で焼いて
in the fire to their gods.”
神々に捧げることまでします」
“If your brother . . . or your son
「あなたの兄弟 あなたの息子 娘
“or your daughter
“or your cherished wife
愛する妻 親友が
“or your closest companion
“should try to entice you in secrecy,
ひそかにあなたを誘おうとして
“saying, ‘Let us go and serve other gods,’
『行ってほかの神々に
仕えよう』と言う場合……
“. . . you must not give in to him or listen to him,
応じたり耳を傾けたりしてはなりません
“nor should you show pity
その人を哀れに思ったり
“or feel compassion or protect him;
同情したり かばったり
すべきでもありません
“instead,
その人を必ず殺すべきです」
you should kill him without fail.”
“Observe the month of Abib,
「アビブの月を覚えていて
あなたの神エホバの
過ぎ越しを祝いなさい
“and celebrate the Passover to Jehovah your God,
“for in the month of Abib, Jehovah your God
あなたの神エホバはアビブの月に
“brought you out of Egypt by night.
夜の間にあなたをエジプトから
連れ出したからです
“And you should sacrifice the Passover offering
エホバがご自分の名のために
選ぶ場所で……
“to Jehovah your God . . . in the place that Jehovah chooses
エホバ神に過ぎ越しの
犠牲を捧げなさい」
to have his name reside.”
Please join me in making a covenant
これらの言葉全てを行うという契約を
with the one true God, Jehovah,
to carry out all the words of this book.
真の神エホバと結びましょう
Jehovah, our God in the heavens . . .
天におられる私たちの神エホバよ…
Amen!
アーメン！
Bring them down to the Kidron Valley, and burn them there.
キデロンの谷で燃やしなさい
And desecrate Topheth,
トフェトを汚して
so that no one can make their son
息子や娘を火で焼くことが
できないようにしなさい
or their daughter pass through the fire there.
This is only the beginning.
戦いはこれからだ
With Jehovah’s help, we will rid the entire land of high places,
エホバの力によって
高い所を
そして偽りの崇拝をかたくなに
推し進める者全てを
every vestige of false worship,
and of everyone who promotes it.
この地から一掃する
Once we cleanse the land of Judah, we’ll head north again
ユダの地を清めたら
もう一度北のサマリア地方に行くのだ
to the cities of Samaria.
Forward!
行け！
To whom do these graves belong?
これは誰の墓だ？
They belong to the Baal prophets, my lord.
バアルの預言者たちです
バアルの預言者の骨を取り
ヤラベアムの祭壇で焼き
Take their bones and burn them
on the altar of King Jeroboam.
Afterward, tear it down.
そして祭壇を取り壊す
What is the grave over there?
こっちは誰の墓だ？
It is the grave of the man of the true God
真の神に仕えた人
who foretold these things
あなたが行ったことを予告した人です
that you have done against the altar of Bethel.
Let him rest.
そのままにしておこう
Do not let anyone disturb his bones.
この人の骨に触れてはならない
バアルよ！
お救いください！
Baal, save us! Baal, save us!
お救いください バアルよ！
Baal! Help us!
おおバアルよ！
扉を閉じろ！
Baal! Baal! Hold it!
私たちをお救いください！
バアル！
助けてください！
Baal! Baal! Hold it!
助けてくれ！
Baal! Help us!
お願いです バアルよ！
父さん
Father.
My lord the king
王なるわが主は
マナセ爺さんの真似事ばかりだ
is a pale imitation of his grandfather.
息子まで私に反抗させるのか
And now he’s turned my own son against me.
反抗じゃないよ これは
正しいことなんだ
That is not true.
This is about standing up for what is right.
バアルは無力なのに…
Baal is powerless.
Why can’t you see that?
どうしてそれが分からないの？
無力だと？
Powerless?
I wish I had sacrificed you in Topheth!
お前をトフェトで
犠牲として捧げておけばよかった！
誰も
No one will ever be able to do that again.
二度とそんなことはできなくなる
ヨシヤがそうしてくれたんだ
Josiah made sure of that.
わが主よ 律法に従って
全て成し遂げられました
My lord,
everything has finally been accomplished according to the Law.
もう1つ行うべきことが残っています
There is one thing left for us to make right.
契約の書にある通り
Command the people to hold a Passover to Jehovah
エホバへの過ぎ越しを行うよう
民に命じてください
as is written in the book of the covenant.
人々が犠牲を用意
できなければどうしますか
What if the people can’t afford the Passover sacrifices?
I will contribute cattle to the people, and my own flocks.
私が牛や羊を寄付します
喜びの時となるでしょう
With great pleasure.
The Passover has not been held in grand style
過ぎ越しは裁き人の時代以来
大規模に行われたことはありません
since the days of the Judges.
「注意して 私が命じるこれらの
全ての言葉に従いなさい
“Be careful to obey all these words that I am commanding you,
“so that it may always go well with you
あなたの神エホバから見て
“and your sons after you,
正しくて良いことを行って
“because you are doing what is good and right
あなたとあなたの子たちにとって
いつも物事がうまくいくためです」
in the eyes of Jehovah your God.”